This is why you see, getting back to
your points about the Gulf states and
and as we talk about the Europeans and
other nations, a lack of trust, a lack
of confidence in the United States. This
is why nations are making the decision
to leave the American order, right? To
embrace this multipolar world. I mean,
essentially, we're looking at this
reality starkly there of the Persian
Gulf, the Straits of Hormuz being
closed, not even being able to put our
ships into the Gulf of Oman
uh because we are trying to fight this
war in a 20th century manner and we're
up against a 21st century adversary. So,
again, you're seeing this this the end
of one age and the beginning of another
year.
Hi, I'm John Kiriakou and welcome back
to Deep Focus.
President Trump addressed the nation on
uh on Wednesday in which he made a
couple of very specific comments related
to the Iran war.
He said that we're winning
and it'll be over in the next two or
three weeks. But, he expressed great
anger at NATO for not participating.
Why? Well, because we're not winning
and he's upset that NATO hasn't jumped
in to help reopen the Strait of Hormuz,
which the Iranians have
closed.
The president also said that
Europe had two choices. They could jump
in and take
their oil by forcing open the Strait of
Hormuz or
they could just buy their oil and gas
from the United States because, he said
disingenuously and wrongly, that the
United States is the greatest producer
of oil and gas in the world. That's not
true.
In any event, he closed his speech by
saying that if the Iranians don't reopen
the Strait of Hormuz in the next two or
three weeks, that he's going to be begin
attacking Iranian um
uh infrastructure, including the
electrical grid.
That's quite literally the definition of
a war crime.
You're not allowed to attack
infrastructure.
International law says so. International
law to which the United States is a
signatory.
So, where do we stand? Well, we're in a
war that we're not winning.
We're in a war without an exit strategy.
And there was a there was a slight
change in Israeli Prime Minister
Benjamin Netanyahu's rhetoric last week,
where a reporter said something about
the American-Israeli war against Iran.
And he said, "It's not an
American-Israeli war against Iran. It's
the American war against Iran, and
Israel is America's ally."
That's not the way I remember this thing
starting.
Well, we're going to talk about all this
with our dear friend, Matthew Hoh. I've
known Matthew for many years. Matthew is
a former State Department Foreign
Service officer, who resigned from the
State Department in protest over
American escalation of war in
Afghanistan. Prior to his assignment in
Afghanistan, Matthew took part in the
American occupation of Iraq, first in
2004, in 2005 in Salahaddin province,
uh with the State Department
Reconstruction and Governance team, and
then again in 2006 and 7 in Anbar
province as a Marine Corps company
commander.
When not deployed, Matthew worked on
Afghanistan and Iraq war policy and
operations issues at the Pentagon and
the State Department from 2002 to 2005.
He has become one of the country's most
important, most prominent, most vocal
whistleblowers on America's misguided
policy in the Middle East and Central
Asia.
Matthew's writings have appeared in such
periodicals as the Atlanta
Journal-Constitution, CNN, The Guardian,
The Huffington Post, USA Today, and
elsewhere. And in 2010 he was named the
Ridenhour Prize recipient for
truth-telling. In 2021, he was awarded
as a defender of liberty by the
Committee for the Republic here in
Washington, D.C. Matthew, welcome back,
buddy.
Hey, John. Thanks for having me back on.
It's good to see you.
Uh I got to tell you, I was beside
myself watching the president's uh
speech to the American people last
night. Now, interestingly enough, it
appeared to be scripted.
Mhm. Did he wing it? Did he write it? Or
do people in the White House really
believe the things that came out of the
president's mouth?
Yeah, I I I wonder about this all the
time. Uh cuz you see when he's making
speeches, he'll say things that nobody
in their right mind would ever put down
on paper, right? And particularly when
he goes
uh off the cuff. He's extra He's he's
just, you know, goes on his tangents.
But I think he probably has a team
around him. One that are so
sycophantic, so loyal to him, um in
lockstep with him, but also too know him
so well right now that they know what he
wants to say. They understand what he's
trying to communicate. And of course,
that communication is not based upon any
sense of of achievable policy, you know,
any uh any any rational argument, any
facts. It's based upon improving the
president's or or or or or or
or demonstrating the president's uh
role, his persona.
Uh
in you know, projecting his ego. Right?
I mean, so I And that's what we saw last
night. We see this just these
mismatches. We see these contradictions
constantly. But you see this bravado and
this boasting that's just not rooted in
anything. And yeah, we're we're in a lot
of trouble here, John. You know, we are
uh you know, in an empire uh that has
been waging these wars that has been uh
uh
uh bankrupting uh our people. Uh you
know, taking
investments that are needed in our
communities and giving them to
corporations and to
crooked
dictatorships overseas.
And we're essentially in an empire that
has a mad emperor in charge. And we're
we're in a lot of trouble.
Matthew, I've been saying for many weeks
that
to win
the United States and Israel would have
to overthrow the Iranian government,
install a pro-US, pro-Israel government
in the what is now the Islamic Republic,
something that will never ever ever
happen.
Uh, and then somehow manage an exit
strategy.
And I I'm unaware of any exit strategy
that exists. For the Iranians to win,
they just have to survive.
And they've survived for 5,000 years.
So, is this a conflict that's winnable
by American standards?
Well, there's a alternative for the
Americans to win that the way in the way
the Americans and the Israelis look at
this, it's to turn Iran into
Syria.
Turn Iran into a failed state, dissolve
Iran
via civil war.
So, I I think there is this belief that
if we can't get regime change, the next
best thing is to make it so that Iran is
simply no longer a factor in the Middle
East. It's so consumed with Iranians
killing Iranians.
And whether the government still stands
or not, whether it it it it it it
resembles Syria or resembles Libya,
is of not really great consequence to us
because the main thing is that we've
taken Iran
off the chessboard, if you will. That
they're no longer a factor and that if
the Iranians are consumed with trying to
maintain power, killing other Iranians
or just staying
staying alive,
then they can't support Hezbollah, they
can't support Ansar Allah, they can't
support the Iraqi resistance, they can't
provide any support for Palestinian
resistance. And I certainly you made
that comment about Netanyahu saying this
is America's war and I think
Netanyahu is communicating there the way
the Israelis do view this in the sense
that
this war on Iran is a supporting effort
to their own efforts for regional
hegemony but also the expansion that the
the
the establishment of greater Israel. So
you know way I look at this is when you
when you back all this out when you
understand it from the Israeli
perspective, removing Iran by an
American war on Iran allows an
annexation of the West Bank to occur,
right? So you have to do all these
steps, you have to prepare, you have to
take out any support whatsoever, whether
it's military, financial, moral,
political, diplomatic that the
Palestinians could have. And so that's
how I also see in this this emphasis on
Lebanon of course. Now Lebanon of course
also falls into that idea or that dream
of greater Israel but for the Israelis
West Bank has been the goal for decades
and so I when you quote Netanyahu there,
it does remind me that for the Israelis
Iran is not the main effort, it's a
supporting effort for them to be able to
eventually annex the West Bank.
Before I ask you the next question, I
want to I want to mention a word from
one of our sponsors. Last week the
Treasury Department put out its
financial report for 2025. Almost no one
covered it.
Here's is it said, 6 trillion in assets,
47 trillion dollars in debt. The US
government is 41
trillion dollars in debt. That's not my
opinion. That's the Treasury
Department's own numbers. A few days ago
Fed Chairman Jerome Powell said the debt
path, quote, will not end well, unquote.
Those are his words. Meanwhile, the big
beautiful bill just added three trillion
dollars more in debt and we're paying
over one trillion dollars a year in
interest on the national debt. I spent
14 years in the CIA. I learned to spot
problems before they blow up.
Right now, central banks all over the
world are buying gold as fast as they
can. China, Poland, India, they all see
what's coming.
Well, we have a free report with
American Alternative Assets called The
Big Beautiful Bubble.
It shows what's really going on going on
and how to protect your savings, your
assets before things get worse. Go to
johnlovesgold.com
for your free copy. That's
or call 1-888-GOLD-053.
Matthew, um
I've said this a million times, but I'm
going to say it again.
Every Israeli Prime Minister
from the mid-1980s
who came to the United States to see
every American president since Ronald
Reagan would say, "Please bomb Iran.
Please bomb Iran. Please bomb Iran." And
every president said, "I'm not going to
bomb Iran for you." Until this one.
Well,
we learned a couple of weeks ago
that Benjamin Netanyahu came to see both
Joe Biden and before him Barack Obama
and said, "If you don't bomb Iran, we're
going to do it and we're going to use
nukes. And both Obama and Biden said,
"Go ahead.
Go ahead and do it."
They called his bluff.
And of course he didn't do it.
He apparently threatened Donald Trump
with the same thing. "Bomb Iran or we're
going to use nukes." And Trump said,
"Okay, I'll bomb Iran. Just don't use
the nukes."
How did we get suckered into this?
Was it really that easy just to tell
Donald Trump we're going to use nukes if
you don't bomb Iran and the next thing
we know we're at war with one of the
strongest, most populous, and most
important countries in the Middle East?
Well, you rightly point out
John that it took Donald Trump as
president to agree to this war. That
previous presidents have been pressured
on it and they'd all avoided it. Uh
George W. Bush seemed to have come
close,
uh but you know, they they smartly
didn't do it. Um and for me, there's a
lot of reasons for this war. Certainly
the Israelis, you know, they're Assemble
everybody in a room who's responsible
for this and the Israelis are sitting in
the front seats, you know, but there's
also other actors, other institutions
here, other interests, the
military-industrial complex, fossil fuel
industry, you know, the tech companies,
they see Iran as a place where 92
million people are not on Facebook or
Instagram or X, right? So there's
there's American commercial interests
that see a marketplace available to
them. But for me, all of those are just
manifestations of the American Empire.
For me, this really comes back to this
is what empires do. That
you know, the United States taking over
from the British Empire in the Middle
East assumes what Britain was trying to
achieve there, what their imperial
objectives were. I mean, you go back to
the idea of the colonization of
Palestine
endorsed by the British, propelled by
the British to the Balfour Declaration.
And then you have Ronald Storrs, who's
one of Britain's uh governor generals uh
it it in in Palestine, you know, saying
in the '20s, "What we're doing here is
we're establishing a loyal Jewish Ulster
in the midst of a potentially hostile
sea of Arabs." I mean, so you see the
imperial purposes of this this colony
this Western colony in the Middle East.
And then, you know, as the United States
takes over from the British, uh
certainly through the Eisenhower and
Kennedy years, there are difficulties
with Iran with with conflicts of
interest. Uh but then when you get to
the Nixon years, you have the
establishment of the Nixon doctrine. And
Richard Nixon seeing the Israelis uh in
the West and then the Iranians under the
Shah in the East as being the cops on
the beat in the Middle East. And the
idea being to contain Arabism. That
we're going to use uh Jewish Israel and
uh uh uh
Persian Iran to contain the Sunni Arabs,
right? Because of particularly in the
'60s and '70s, the threat of pan-Arabism
was of grave concern to the American
empire. Uh
we you know, then that, you know,
develops further. You get into the '80s.
You have the establishment of modern
Hasbara, uh you know, particularly after
Ronald Reagan
rebukes uh Israel Menachem Begin
following uh Israel's brutal invasion of
Lebanon. Uh the Israelis recognize that
we need to have more control of the
situation. And now you have this other
aspect of the United States. It's
certainly an empire, but it also is a
government of legalized bribery. And the
Israelis, just like so many other
industries, institution, interest, etc.,
have recognized that. And they have been
successful in essentially, you know,
basically, my opinion is the American
empire has sold off its organs for the
highest bidder. And so Middle East
foreign policy has gone to the Israelis.
They bid the most. They paid the most
for it. You know, just like our health
care policies, just like our
agricultural policies, right? Just like
you name it in the sense of how how does
our government decide policy whether
it's domestic or foreign, it goes to the
highest bidder essentially. Um and so
that that's that's how I see the
evolution of this and that's how I see
you getting to a point then where you
have this inertia, whether it's an
imperial inertia because again you have
now you have this country Iran that has
to be repudiated, has to be punished for
1979.
It's also standing up against the
hegemon. It's standing it's it's a it
it's sticking up and and and giving a
finger, right, to the empire. You can't
allow that. It's supporting other groups
that are doing the same. It's ruining
our ambitions for dominance, etc. etc.
etc. But on the other side end as well
then you have this uh uh capture of
American Middle Eastern policy
uh by the Israel lobby. And so the two
things finally uh culminate in Donald
Trump's presidency because now you have
a president who's malleable enough,
who's foolish enough, who's ahistoric
enough, however you want to describe
him, to go along with this. And I I that
to me is how we have arrived in this
absolutely ridiculous and stupid uh war.
Uh not to me not to, you know, the uh uh
uh also to say it's illegal. It's going
to be counterproductive. It's immoral,
right? Etc. etc. etc.
Matthew, I I've got to ask you. I'm a
frequent visitor to the Persian Gulf. Um
I spent the better part of my career
there, Kuwait, Bahrain, Saudi Arabia. I
go to the United Arab Emirates
relatively regularly.
And it seems like the the governments of
those countries are of two minds.
Or three minds.
Number one, they dislike, in some cases
they hate, Iran and they distrust Iran.
They fear Iran at the same time.
But they know that it's a rough
neighborhood and they have to live in
it. Okay.
Number two, the Saudis spent 10 years
trying to finally normalize relations
with Iran. They did that.
Behind the scenes, we're hearing that
the Saudis, the Emiratis, the Bahrainis,
maybe even the Kuwaitis have been urging
the United States to go for it,
overthrow this government, and let the
chips fall.
At the same time,
there is a significant US Army presence
in Kuwait, in Saudi Arabia, and the
Emirates, and in Oman.
The
headquarters of the Fifth Fleet is in
Bahrain, and the US Air Force has the
world's largest airbase at Al Udeid in
Qatar.
Having all this American military
presence is supposed to protect these
countries from Iran.
And it and it hasn't. The Iranians have
been able to use these these cheap,
domestically built drones, suicide
drones, packed with explosives, fly them
into hotels, blow up the runways of the
airports in Kuwait and Bahrain, blow up
fuel storage tanks at Dubai Airport, and
essentially, scare the daylights out of
everybody. So, on the one hand,
do these countries really want this war
to continue and for the US to overthrow
the Iranian government, or do they want
the war to end so life can go back to
normal and everybody can start making
money again?
Or are they going to have to question
the wisdom of the US military presence?
If the US can't protect them,
why be there in the first place? What
are your thoughts on this?
Yeah, that's a great analysis, John. I'd
add to that these countries don't like
each other.
You know, certainly the conflict between
the Saudis and the Emiratis uh, very
clear in the last year. you know, the
Saudis militarily evicting the Emirates
from, uh, Yemen. Uh, it was just a few
years ago, four, five years ago, you
had, uh, the other Gulf states
blockading, uh, Qatar. And that looked
like that was going to turn into a war.
Uh, so you have these tensions, these
conflicts, these this lack of trust, if
you will, between these countries
themselves. So I think for many years
the American presence, them all being
vassals in the American empire, uh, was
a stabilizing uh, had a stabilizing
effect. Uh, your point though, uh, is
that the Iranians have demonstrated, uh,
to the region that these bases, uh, this
American presence doesn't make you
safer, it makes you a target. Uh,
that the guarantee of security from the
Americans was false, it was hollow. Uh,
and just as the general agreement that
the United States had with the world
essentially, uh, following the Second
World War, that the United States would
guarantee the the freedom of of movement
of of critical energy supplies out of
the Middle East was what the United
States was was was giving the world in
exchange for its dominance, right? You
let us lead essentially, and we will
provide these benefits to you. And that
has turned out to be a farce as well.
And again, you know, certainly people
watching, listening are all saying,
"Yeah, that's what happens when you have
a declining empire, you know, this is
you know, the Iranians are just poking
holes and showing us what we all know
how how corrupted, how faded, how
dysfunctional it was under the facade."
Uh, but this question that you're
asking, what should the Gulf states be
doing? Well, one I I I think these Gulf
states recognize that they owe their
positions, say particularly the monarch
in Manama, the the the the the the the
ruling family in in Bahrain, they owe
their positions to the American
presence, right? I mean, and and
certainly, the the other families in the
region, uh,
you know, more secure, uh, but they also
recognize that the good thing they have
going is because of their relationship
with the United States.
Uh, but that's juxtaposed now up against
the reality that the United States not
just can't protect them, but won't
protect them. You know, in this
hierarchy of of of of of of states
within the empire, they are far below
Israel. There's Israel and then there's
everybody else. The Ukrainians have
learned this out. I mean, we uh,
probably I probably said this to you.
We've talked about that Ukraine was
going to be the next Afghanistan, right?
In terms of how we were going to treat
allies. And now we're seeing this with
the Gulf States. Uh, so, you know, this
determination of what the Gulf States
want to do is is of course tainted by
the fact that you have these corrupt
monarchs in power who see that their
power has been based in the presence of
the United States. So, why are they
going to give that up? But they are
staring into the stark reality of the
jeopardy of maintaining this
relationship with the United States. I
mean, the the the the harm that's come
to them already and that will continue
to come this war goes on. Um, and I'm
not certain why, uh, anyone would be in
favor extending this war cuz continue as
the more the war goes on, the more it's
in Iran's favor.
But, you know, certainly, you know, they
have their I'm assuming they have their
machinations, how they see a shattered
dysfunctional Iran spewing millions of
refugees through the region, uh,
permanently closing the Straits of
Hormuz is somehow in their favor. Uh, I
don't I don't really understand, but,
um, again, these men owe their positions
to,
uh,
the presence of the United States and I
think just as you see with the Europeans
wanting to hold on to NATO, wanting to
hold on to something that has, uh, uh,
put them in power, kept them in power,
wanting to keep the status quo. But
this, you know, gets to the point then,
John, that this war to me is going to be
a or maybe, I should say a radically
transformative event in history that
this will be the event that historians
say this is when the American century
ends. This is when the 20th century ends
and this is where the multipolar world
begins. This is where the 21st century
begins. Now of course, you know, we're
already in the multipolar world but
historians like to have something to
mark, you know, as a start date in
history and I think this could be very
much that.
I want to I want to ask you one more
question about the Strait of Hormuz
before we move on to other issues. I do
want to talk about NATO and Lebanon as
well. But, you know, back in the 1980s,
Matthew,
uh
there was a conflict between, well, Iran
and the United States, Iran and the Arab
Gulf states
and the Reagan administration responded
by
by putting American flags on
on oil tankers
carrying Kuwaiti oil and escorting them
with the US Navy escorting them through
the Strait of Hormuz.
Uh right now the Strait of Hormuz is
effectively closed.
One ship got through last week and it
was it was an Indian flag tanker
carrying oil to China
and the Indian ship paid a toll to the
Iranian government. The Iranians allowed
them to to
go through unmolested.
Besides that, 65%
of the world's fertilizer goes through
the Strait of Hormuz. We're going to get
to the point where we're going to go
into a global food crisis if if
fertilizer can't make its way through
the Strait.
Do you see the US Navy
escorting ships? Do you see the US
government reflagging tankers or cargo
ships? Do you see the US Navy attacking
the Iranians more ferociously and trying
to take control of of the Strait of
Hormuz. How does this end up working
out?
You know,
in the '80s when we when we reflagged
those tankers and escorted them, we had
a much more capable navy, a larger navy,
of course, but
also one that was able to actually have
a presence in the Persian Gulf. Our navy
is a thousand kilometers away from the
Straits of Hormuz right now. We can't
get any closer than that. Um I mean, so
just one is just a difference in
warfare, what's available to adversaries
now in terms of missiles and drones and
satellite tracking and things like that.
But uh you know, the reality too that
you have a
a superficiality here with the American
military. You have a hollowed-out vapid
force. You have
a defense industry that for years can't
produce ships or planes that aren't
maintenance nightmares. You have a navy
that we can't even put all our ships
underway cuz we simply don't have enough
sailors to man them. A- as well then
too, you see the Gerald Ford, the $13
billion aircraft carrier, the newest and
most expensive and largest warship ever
built. And uh she's in port now uh
because of a of a laundry fire. I mean,
so I mean, there's so many we could have
a whole conversation just ex-
unwrapping that. Where's the damage
control? Why every sailor is supposed to
be a firefighter? It took you guys 30
hours to put out a dry laundry room
fire? Right? I mean, so you know, that
>> that, the toilet didn't work.
Well, the toilet didn't work. The toilet
never worked on that ship. So, but it
gets to the point that we have a navy
that for $13 billion,
you know, damage control is what they're
supposed to build those ships around.
That's the idea of a warship, supposed
to be able to survive contact, survive
damage. So, they build these warships
with damage control as something that
they build around. And then again, this
idea that, you know, in the Marine
Corps, every Marine is a rifleman, and
in the sa- in the navy, every sailor is
a firefighter. And it took you 30 hours
to put out this fire? You know, so it
shows you again the design, the
construction, what our forces are
actually equipped with, how just that
these they're not built for warfare. The
purpose of the military-industrial
complex is not to build warships that
can protect American interests, is to
make profits for weapons companies. And
the same thing too, you have a force
that a
personnel force a
combat force that can't do the
rudimentary basic things that all
sailors all navies have required since
the dawn of of navies, since the first
naval ship took took took to sail. You
know, so I mean, I think in that it show
it gets to the what you're talking about
here about the impossibility of this,
the impracticality of this, the fantasy
of the United States forcing its way
through the Strait of Hormuz, and the
fact that all this information was was
was knowledgeable. All this was was
understood. Nothing occurred in the last
4 weeks that made this any different
than the previous 4 weeks were in terms
of the actual capacity and capabilities
and readiness and
abilities of the American military.
So you have an American military that
can't meet the objectives of the US
president. Now this is an objective that
the president caused by his disastrous
choice to launch a war of aggression,
but still the American military cannot
achieve the objectives of the president.
And I think, you know, again we can get
start talking again about decline of the
American empire and everything, but this
is a real aspect of that. And this is
why you see, getting back to your points
about the Gulf States and
we talk about the Europeans and other
nations, a lack of trust, a lack of
confidence in the United States. This is
why nations are making a decision to
leave the American order, right? To
embrace this multipolar world. I mean,
essentially we're looking at this
reality starkly there of the Persian
Gulf, the Strait of Hormuz being closed,
not even being able to put our ships
into the Gulf of Oman,
uh because we are trying to fight this
war in a 20th century manner, and we're
up against a 21st century adversary. So
again, you're seeing this this the end
of one age and the beginning of another
here.
You're 100% right about that. The nature
of warfare has changed, and it's like it
just hasn't occurred to us yet.
Before we get to NATO, cuz I have some
specific
>> It It hasn't It's occurred to John It's
occurred to It's occurred to you and I.
And it's occurred to These people are
smart enough to know it, but they know
that changing the status quo
means they lose their business model.
Right? And whether the business model is
a policy-based business model, whether
it's it's a campaign-donation-based
business model, whether it's it's
military industrial. I remember John
working
in procurement during the Iraq War
trying to find technologies to find
suicide bombers, going to a meeting and
there are all these executives from
these defense companies there. And
waiting to go into the meeting and
hearing these executives talking in the
the passageway in the hallway, and you
know, saying essentially, "I can't wait
for this war to be over so we can go
back to business." Right? Business as
usual, right? I mean, that's the that's
the mindset there.
Business as usual, yeah.
Before before we go to NATO, I have to
ask you about Lebanon. This
most recent Israeli
invasion of Lebanon has been
particularly brutal.
The Israelis appear to
to be in the process of creating what
looks like a safe zone, a no-man's land
south of the Litani River.
And there are 900,000
internally displaced civilians.
Lebanon's already a failed state for a
whole bunch of reasons.
This just makes it worse. It's a It's a
level of human misery that is almost
unparalleled in the Middle East right
now. Although, I guess you could draw
comparisons with with Yemen.
Is there any
upside to any of this? Is there any good
news for the Lebanese? Is there any way
to get out of this or are we going to
see the continued slow-motion
destruction of Lebanon as a country?
I think it's the latter. I mean, I I
hate to say that, but I just don't see
the Israelis pulling back from their
objectives here. Again, this objective
of Lebanon and certainly you go back to
the Israelis and they talked that they
spoke of how Israel should go to the
Litani River, you know, to 20 km to 30
km or so into into Lebanon.
Um
I just don't see the Israelis backing
away from this.
Um this is and many of Israelis have
said this, October 7th gave them the
best chance they're ever going to have
and they're going to capitalize on it.
They're going to take advantage of this
moment. They finally had an American
president who would attack Iran, who
would do this work that they need done
in order to now carry out these other
aspects of greater Israel. They've
neutralized
Syria
by helping to get an Al-Qaeda boss, you
know, that's a whole conversation we can
have there. I know that
that upsets you as much as upsets me,
right? You know, and I don't want to
shouldn't get us started on that. But,
you know, but with the Lebanese, I think
with the Lebanese though, it is they are
in this position where who's going to
remove the Israelis? The Israelis just
killed three UN peacekeepers the other
day. They don't care. I mean, what's
going to force the Israelis out of it?
Even if Donald Trump was to
end the war tomorrow in Iran, the
Israelis are not pulling out of Lebanon.
I think this this time this presence
there is going to be permanent. It will
look, I think, like a no-man's land as
you described it. I know there are
Israeli settlers who are trying to get
in,
but again, for me the purposes for the
Israelis are to create that buffer zone.
I mean again and and many do want the
greater Israel project there as well.
But the idea being having this buffer
zone that their flank, their northern
flank is secure so that when they focus
on fully annexing the West Bank, which
is a project that's already underway,
they won't have to provide too much
attention to Lebanon. You know, again as
a supporting effort the same way too.
Hopefully the Israelis are thinking by
the time Trump lets up Iran will be
if it's still standing and it's not in a
civil war then at least it'll be in a
place where it can't really provide much
support. It can't really affect our
operations in the West Bank. It can't
fire missiles and drones at us or it
would choose not to do so because it's
been deterred by our war on them. So
yeah, with regards to the Lebanese I
really wish I had something other to say
but I don't see and the same for the
Palestinians. I don't see
where the help is going to come from.
Yeah. Just as an aside, I had dinner a
couple of weeks ago with a senior
Turkish government official
and we were talking about Syria and I
said about President Ahmed al-Jarrah
I said, he has to be a CIA asset, right?
I mean how can you be a senior Al-Qaeda
figure, the the
deputy founder of ISIS
and then the US supports your your
ascension to the presidency of of Syria.
He has to be CIA and the Turk said, oh
no he's ours. We put him in there.
And I said, you know what? That actually
makes perfect sense.
It it does make sense. Yeah.
>> And I I do want to I do want to upset
everybody by reminding them of the
conversation that he had with David
Petraeus though last September where
Petraeus the former CIA director did say
to him, your success is our success. So
just to just to upset anybody who they
wasn't going well. Remember that, yeah.
That's exactly right. In the meantime,
Jews and Christians are being literally
massacred. Quite literally massacred,
which is exactly what you and I said was
going to happen.
You know, whether you like Bashar
al-Assad or not, whether you like his
politics or not, he was the only thing
standing between minority communities
and complete annihilation.
And that's what's happened.
So, let me ask you about NATO.
Um Donald Trump said last night uh that
he is, his words, "absolutely
considering withdrawing from NATO." He's
not going to withdraw from NATO, but the
fact that he would just speak those
words weakens the alliance.
We also learned last week that
in the midst of this
bizarro world
claim to Greenland,
uh the Danish military
quietly and literally in the middle of
the night sent plane loads of explosives
to Greenland to blow up their own
airport runways
to try to at least temporarily forestall
what they believed might be an American
invasion.
This is Denmark.
We're talking about invading
Denmark.
Has enough damage been done to the
alliance that NATO is done?
Um do you think the United States will
withdraw? Even if it doesn't withdraw,
can NATO survive this administration?
I think
who knows what Donald Trump is going to
do, right? Who and it so certainly is a
possibility that he would try and
withdraw the United States from NATO. It
requires an act of Congress to do that.
That's not going to happen.
>> Yes. Right? So, now you'd have a reduced
relationship as long as Trump is in the
White House.
Uh
and I think what the Europeans are
counting on is for the Democrats to take
control of the White House in '28. Um
you know
I think for many of those in power
throughout Europe, uh again, they are
the same mindset. They are living in the
20th century and NATO is a 20th century
structure. NATO is not suited for the
21st century. But structures like NATO
are what keep people like Starmer,
Emerts, and Macron and von der Leyen in
power, right? Kaja Kallas, who is I
believe who is the foreign minister
of the EU is is a must go to bed at
night thinking about becoming or
replacing Ursula von der Leyen as the
head of the EU. And of course in Kallas'
mind, if you're paying attention to what
she says, the idea for Kallas may be
then, and here I'm speculating, but
okay, if we lose NATO, then we'll get
our EU army. So again, here's another
here's another
aspect of this where you see this
transformative effect of this war, this
splintering of Look,
the Iraq war in 2003 was incredibly
unpopular. But the British sent 45,000
troops to take part in the invasion. The
Spanish and the Italians that just
closed their space for US with this war
had thousands of troops in the Iraq war.
And now you're seeing this type of you
know, there's a spectrum of course on
where the Europeans are, Spain and Italy
on one side, but even like the Germans,
even Friedrich Merz, who last year
declared that the Israelis were doing
our dirty work with Iran, and certainly
Merz and Starmer and Macron and their
governments have as much to blame for
this situation because they went along
with the
disbandment of the JCPOA. They were the
ones who pushed the snapback sanctions
into effect in the fall. That's was the
precipitate cause of the collapse of the
Iranian economy, the the collapse of the
Iranian rial last winter, right? I mean,
like all these things the Europeans have
their hands in as well, but they
recognize that this war is just too
much. I mean, my God, if the Iraq war
wasn't too much for them, but this war
is too much for them, it shows one just
how much of a folly this war is, too,
but just how much things have changed.
So, the Europeans in power want to hold
on to NATO because they believe that
those type of structures that keep us in
power, they want the status quo. They've
got their fingers crossed that Gavin
Newsom or Gretchen Whitmer or AOC or
somebody takes the White House in '28
and then things can go back to normal
and the Europeans can be the junior
partners in the American empire.
Others I think are looking at a sense
of, "Okay, if we lose NATO, here's an
opportunity for Europe to now come into
the multipolar world as its own
confederation, as its own block, as its
own organism, however you want to
describe it."
But, you know, those I think anyone
who's thinking that way would be like a
Callus who sees it for her own
ambitions. But, for the most part, those
who are ruling in power right now look
at NATO as one of those structures that
is a good thing. It It keeps them in
power. It It is the infrastructure upon
which they sit. So, again, looking
backwards to the 20th century, and
that's one of the reasons why Europe is
in the condition it's in. You know,
Europe has had a really Why, John?
Following the end of the Cold War, the
Europeans didn't go on their own way. If
they had, we can imagine now a Europe
that is a global hub of technology,
right?
A global maybe maybe a global hub for
education,
you know, what have you. Instead, the
Europeans went along with our wars, they
took part in our wars, they embraced our
neoliberal fantasies for their
economics, right? And now they are
countries by and large that are hollowed
out, whose people are dealing with
housing problems, health care problems,
cost of life issues, as well then, too,
issues regarding immigration. I mean,
you name it, the Europeans are
struggling with it right now. And their
mindset, uh this goes back to this
conversation about NATO looking back to
the past, being in the 20th century,
their mindset is that we're going to
embrace a military Keynesianism, and
that will get us out of this.
Politically, our identity, particularly
with the Russian wars, dependent upon
it. That's what we're going to use to
distract our population, foreign wars,
foreign menaces, right? So, a military a
political Keynesianism, if you will, uh
through militarization. But then also,
too, the main thing is we're going to
get our economies out of this through a
Keynesianism, but we're going to invest
all this money, we're going to practice
austerity, we're going to further take
from our people, further deny real
investments that return something to our
people, and we're going to put that
money into our weapons industries. And I
think everybody knows exactly how that's
going to go.
Before we move on to uh Palestine, uh
another word from one of our sponsors.
If there's one thing that we've learned
over the last few years, it is that
access to medication can change quickly
depending on politics, regulation, and
corporate influence. That is why it's
important to have a pharmacy that
focuses on access and transparency, not
on bureaucracy. And that's the reason
why people are turning to All Family
Pharmacy.
Instead of scheduling doctor visits,
sitting in waiting rooms, and dealing
with insurance approvals, the entire
process is handled online. You choose
the medications you need on their
website, you fill out a short medical
form, and a licensed doctor reviews your
request. If it's appropriate, they
provide the prescription, and then they
ship directly to your door. It's a
simple way to keep essential medications
on hand like antibiotics, antivirals,
ivermectin, mebendazole, NAD+, and more
than 400 other prescription medications
people rely on every day.
Prepare now before you need it in the
future. Visit all family pharmacy/john
and use promo code John10 to save 10% on
your next order.
So, Palestine, Matthew,
we can't have a conversation like this
without talking about Palestine.
Um Gaza essentially has been destroyed.
Hundreds of thousands of people are
still on the move. There's not enough
food. There's not enough water. There's
not a single functioning hospital.
There's no electricity, not enough
medications, and the Israeli government
won't let NGOs or even the American
government provide relief. We had
Anthony Aguilar on the show a couple of
weeks ago, and he told an absolutely
grim story about the situation on the
ground in Gaza.
So,
is Gaza
done?
Is Donald Trump going to get his wish of
forcing out every Palestinian so he can,
his words, make it better than Monte
Carlo?
Is this a real estate play? And what
does all this mean for the West Bank as
the Israelis turn their attention there?
I I think um
what we're looking at here is a
population of the Palestinian population
in Gaza uh living in now roughly 40%
of what the Gaza Strip once was. Uh the
Israelis have taken approximately 60% of
the Gaza Strip. Uh I think there's going
to be some tension as to whether that
becomes
Israeli settlements or Trump high-rises.
Uh right? So, whether we see settler
caravans or Trump casinos,
um we'll we'll we'll we'll see. Uh but
certainly, you know, it gets back to
this idea we're talking about with
Lebanon. Who's going to get them out?
Who's going to force the Israelis or the
Americans? And the the cruel thing about
Gaza and it's well the
2 million people in Gaza, there's 2
million cruel things occurring every
day. But this reality that this board of
peace, this plan for Gaza,
this
structure that has been put in place is
international law.
I mean this betrayal of the Palestinian
people by the international community,
by enshrining Donald Trump's board of
peace as an act of UN Security Council
which makes it international law. I mean
it what's to be done? What's to be done
about this? And so I think the
Palestinians are going to suffer
and will continue to suffer and the
conditions the plan is to make it so
horrible and to slowly let some out that
eventually you get to a point where they
start dying off
not too quickly to attract the world's
attention, but you know, enough so that
the pressure is there so that eventually
Egypt will let them in or some cruise
ship will come along and pick them up
and take them to some country the United
States has bribed to allow them there.
You know, and this is a project that's
been going on it goes back to the Biden
administration finding some place for
the Palestinians to go to. You know, the
Biden administration had money set aside
to build tank camps in the Sinai for a
tent city in the Sinai for all the
Palestinians from Gaza as well as
understanding that the Israelis were
running around the country running
around the world trying to find somebody
to take these people in. And so
eventually the right bribe will be given
to the right country and that
opportunity will be presented to the
Palestinians and some will take it
because
you're going to sit
there and watch your children starve to
death
you know, and others won't. But all of
this then sets up the annexation of the
West Bank. I mean
it's already there in
our language, John. You and I don't do
this and the good folks watching and
listening don't do this, but the way
Palestine is discussed, it's already
separate enclaves. It has been, you
know, physically for years, but at least
with our language we always try to stay
Palestine. But now it's very difficult
to get that point across that Gaza and
the West Bank are the same land.
And the Israelis and Americans have been
very effective at cutting that.
And, you know, the plan for the
Israelis in the West Bank and they have
said this outright
is to essentially you have in in
the West Bank under the Oslo Accords
there West Bank was divided into area A,
B, and C. Area C complete Israeli
control. Area B
more village areas that were under mixed
control but mainly most of the Israelis
controlled it. And in area A were the
large urban areas that were fully under
control of the Palestinian Authority.
Area C is fully controlled by the
Israelis. Area B is being winnowed away
every day. People are being driven out
of the villages into the cities and the
idea basically is that you will have
seven or eight urban areas that will
continually be chiseled away.
You know, thousands of homes will
continually be demolished but that these
urban areas will be where the
Palestinians are gathered into
essentially concentration camps
and that they will be left to die on the
vine there. They will not be able to
support one another. They will be cut
off from one another.
Settlers will continue to fill the
spaces between these urban areas and
that they will sometimes be reduced,
particularly the places that the
Israelis hate like Jenin and Nablus.
They will reduce those parts of those
cities but other places like Ramallah
will be left to just
die, die on the vine. And in other
places like Hebron where you have
settlers already mixed into the city,
you will see a
greater fortification by the Israeli
military within the city and and a
greater persecution of the Palestinians
living there. And so eventually, 10
years from now,
you have
essentially an annexed
West Bank that has been taken over
through Israeli ownership, both de facto
and de jure.
And you have these concentration camps
that we once called cities
where the Palestinians are
are being immiserated, they're
suffering, and they're slowly dying. And
again, of course, hope that the
good friend of the Israelis and the
Americans, King Hussein, opens his
borders or something like that, and
that's how they get rid of the problem.
One last question for you, Matthew.
The Democrats are widely projected to
to take the House of Representatives
back in November in the midterm
elections.
The polls are showing as many as 40
seats possibly flipping.
Those same polls show that the Democrats
have a real chance of winning the US
Senate. If they if they win every close
race, the Democrats could take the
Senate 51-49.
But does any of that matter in terms of
policy toward Iran, toward Israel,
toward Palestine, toward Lebanon?
No.
No. Um Yeah, it didn't seem so. It will
be similar, John, to what we saw when
the Democrats took control of the
Congress in 2006. And the Democrats felt
that allowing the Iraq war to continue
would better their chances to take the
White House in 2008. And that's what
you'll see here, too, as well. Plus
also, too, you have many members of the
Democratic Party, particularly in the
leadership positions, who believe in
what the United States is doing, who
believe in this Iran war. They certainly
they temper their statements or they try
and speak out of both sides of their
mouth because they understand how
unpopular war is, particularly within
the Democratic Party. But certainly you
see people Chuck Schumer, Hakeem
Jeffries, you know, etc.
uh who are supportive of this war
and uh you know, so I don't see them
doing anything if they come into power
next January that limits the president's
foreign policy,
uh you know, limits his wars, uh you
know, I think their triangulation, their
calculus will be how do we allow him to
keep doing things that will give us a
better chance to win the White House in
'28, but these things are also what they
would believe in. I mean, this is why
there are political consequences for
war. We've seen it in 2006, 2008, we saw
it in 2016, but that just changes the
party in power. That just changes the
color of the shirt of the person who's
sitting in the seat. It doesn't change
the imperial structure. It doesn't
change the American empire. And you
know, you have two parties that are a
uniparty when it comes to the imperial,
you know, the imperial aspects of the
United States. And so, I think
regardless of what happens in November,
you don't have a change in the war
machine or the war state because that is
the structure upon which everything is
built.
Matthew Hoh, thank you so much for for
being with us and for explaining these
very complicated issues. I I wish I
could say that that I was optimistic
about things, but like you,
I'm really not. And I think that there's
no difference between the Democrats and
the Republicans on these issues. You
know, when when Benjamin Netanyahu comes
to Washington, which he does quite
frequently, and he goes up to Capitol
Hill to see his friends, and Democratic
senators are literally running through
the hall like O.J. Simpson through an
airport in the old '70s commercial,
so that they could get a photo op with
Netanyahu before he leaves the building,
you know we're in trouble.
Right. Well, they they they they had the
votes according to Ryan Grim and the
folks at the at
Drop Site News and the as well as at The
Intercept, I believe, the Democrats had
the votes in the house to pass a war
powers resolution. It wouldn't have
mattered because the Senate had rejected
it, but still you'd have a votes on
record on this. And Hakeem Jeffries and
the Democratic Party leadership didn't
we have that vote. They decided to go on
recess, on vacation. What's more
important than voting on issues of war
and peace for these members of Congress?
It's obviously one not getting your name
on record, not stopping this war, doing
something to stop this war, but also
two, the more important thing is getting
back home to your districts, shaking
hands, and collecting
checks, right?
Isn't that the truth?
Well, Matthew, thanks again for joining
us. Always love talking to you, and and
thanks for setting us straight on some
of these issues. Appreciate it very
much. I look forward to seeing you again
soon. Thank you, John. All the best,
buddy.
Ladies and gentlemen, thank you for
joining us for another episode of of
Deep Focus. We can only continue to do
this because of you. So, thanks for
watching, thanks for liking, sharing,
subscribing, and all that good stuff.
Please keep it up. We'll see you next
time.